all right welcome back everyone it is
October
17th and we're in our second discussion
on chapter
two so
let's head over there and
um first does
anybody interesting little colors were
added does anyone want
to give
any opening thoughts or
Reflections on chapter two or just bring
up some
question so I could
share
briefly comparison to
the previous
sections uh it took me longer for
sure and I had to do more uh search for
more reference material because I think
it's the first section that's
really trying to introduce the the
mathematics um of the
framework
and uh the the first Parts where we're
discussing uh very free energy which is
only taking into account information
about the past and the present
to um to compute uh free
energy
um this was relatively
straightforward um I think the section
on expected free energy is a more
significant
leap and I think I need to spend more
time I'm
um uh analyzing that and and really
making sense
of of that part of of the
chapter awesome thank
you anyone else want again just any part
of two that stuck with him or a question
they have or a a thought on the role of
the low rad
um I will just uh Echo the sentiment
that um I I think I I finally you know
um got the handle on free energy as a
concept but the expected free energy is
still completely impenetrable making
that that that um uh cognitive leap is
is is is still a little bit beyond
beyond my
Reach cool we can definitely look over
it okay at the at the uh at the very
small font
overview we have perception as inference
so it's still
passive
is even though we can discuss there are
some ways of action is related to even
what might be seen as passive inference
background on basian statistics
example on the background on basian
statistics which we can look at again
but there's an object in a person's hand
and they're updating their beliefs about
what they think that object is based
upon what they observe it might be an
apple it might be a frog and then they
see it jump and they update their belief
from thinking that it's probably an
apple to probably a frog
um that case is carried through in the
exact basian setting and for smaller
State spaces and smaller scale
computational problems you can utilize
exact
base however for larger State spaces you
can't always do exact Bay and so that
requires an approximation method and
variational free energy or the evidence
lower bound is a common approximation
method for doing variational basy
inference
um doing approximate basian inference is
then mobilized in this particular
partition cybernetic
setting which leads to a discussion of
action still we're in
the um cybernetic setting continuing to
discuss like perception and action as
part of this unified approximation
challenge
then we get to the real
equations equation 2.5 and 2.6 are like
the two key equations in this chapter
2.5 is the variational free energy so
here is where we have um the ability to
build on people's work previously and
also make massive massive um
contributions with our studying here in
2.
five previous cohorts have used the
ontology to provide natural language
descriptions of the
equation so if this just looks like a
lot of
symbology then it may be helpful to
read the ontology description of
it 2.5 variational free energy is about
beliefs and data so variational free
energy is like the real
time um sense making Vibe check it's
very closely related to how surprising
incoming observations are given
beliefs some more discussion on how the
kale diversions comes into
play and then it goes from consideration
of the real-time variational free energy
into the future oriented expected free
energy and planning as inference with
equation
2.6 but that's not something that all
cognitive systems necessarily do not all
systems engage in explicit planning and
then there's some discussions about
special cases of expected free energy
and that's the end of the low road so
chapter 2 pretty much starts with a
simple exact Baye
setting slides over to the approximate
variational case applies it to
cybernetics and then introduces the two
key equations in 2.5 and
2.6 variational and expected free
energy just to kind of give an overview
but but like so as as you have
highlighted like those are the exact
things to pick up in the low
road
so anyone else want to just bring up any
thought or question or what what area
can we go
to yeah I think maybe before we move on
to the more
technical uh
details I think it's important
to to highlight the significance of this
jump like it's a a conceptual
leap that was very striking to me and I
think after you spent some
time um studying this kind of area it's
it becomes kind of intuition but but
this idea of perception as
inference um in contrast to what at
least throughout my life the way that
I've thought about seeing things has
been this the straight transction from
from objects in the world
to uh just lights on my retina and then
some processing processing through my
brain and then just kind of this image
being projected
somewhere um but the the predictive
aspect the the inferential top down
component of it is is I think it's a
remarkable idea and it's interesting
that um this isn't
it's not really something that you can
tell at least I I have couldn't couldn't
tell just by
observing
how I look at the world at least
not not earlier in my life so so
I'm I just wanted to highlight that as a
as an interesting uh but significant
like a significant leap I think in in
thinking about
perception
yes Sarah and then anyone
else hello I have a disclosure a comment
and a question so my disclosure is I
read the wrong
chapter I missed two weeks so I thought
I'd missed two chapters but obviously I
didn't uh I did read this chapter but I
read it like six months ago so I'm just
flicking through very fast now so that
my disclosure my comment is yeah I
totally get the idea it's such a it's
such like a a flip to go from this idea
of light coming in your eyes I remember
in primary school being told off for
doing it the wrong way feeling like
light goes out and she's like no it goes
in and like we we kind of grow up with
this idea like we're sensory machines
but then I feel like once you make the
flip it's all predictive you it's really
actually hard to go back and like not
see it anymore and then my question was
so is I guess it does relate to this
chapter which is lucky because you know
that's what we're actually on so like
figure 2.5 right so You' got this idea
of the perception and the action and one
thing I've been struggling with is the
how they're different right because
perception changing your perception is
actually an internal action so it's
you're updating a model well what's that
that's changing a synaptic way that's an
action but it's just being performed
internally so one thing I've didn't
realize I was struggling with this till
today is uh yeah how why is perception
separate to action and I know like the
idea is it's a unified theory of
perception action but why do we still
have those and how are they different am
I missing something so thank
you
yes
yeah okay H how how are perception and
action um similar and different and
related okay and
Kristoff um so I just want to say kind
of couple things I like this idea of
this what s just said about light light
going out rather than and reminded me of
a quote from uh kard that life has to be
lived forwards but uh can only be
understood backwards and there's there's
something about the way we explain the
world
um you know to ourselves or other is
that has this kind of like inversion
quality to it and and and um I kind of I
can't put my finger on it precisely yet
but I I see there's a kind of some kind
of universal phenomenon that's that's
lurking there but um about this leap
from you know uh perception to to
inference I remember one of the uh
earlier papers by Carl Frist he
mentioned something really fascinating
and he mentions the hubel and wisel um
uh experiments with um cat retina I
don't know if you um if all of you are
familiar with that but they basically
were Shining Light um uh onto Cuts uh
retina an aized cat and measuring
response from some um um some neuron
there for you know measuring electric
response and they found these recept
these ideas receptive fields that
responded to various kinds of
orientations and and and so on and the
interesting phenomenon that they
couldn't explain was end stopping so
when you have a receptive field you know
like it will it will respond to the
specific neuron will respond to some
specific orientation and specific length
of the um of the rectangle that we're
projecting but when the rectangle gets
wide enough it stops
and the question was why and uh
Neuroscience couldn't quite explain this
but uh uh sort of you know predictive um
the sort of predictive framework um uh I
remember Carl mentioned that in one of
his papers it starts to suddenly makes
sense because kind of in nature you
don't really see short lines so when
you're projecting a when when you're
looking at the Horizon it's always a
very very long line but if it becomes
shorter then it's you know it's
something that um does not occur in
nature and therefore for the neuron
fires because it actually is a
prediction error so it's kind of
fascinating that uh um this this
inversion of this idea suddenly suddenly
made a phenomenon um you know uh
explainable which I thought was really
really
interesting yes
so first this uh like coming in and out
of the eye
um it is really a different view on
perception when as as um was brought up
like whether we think about well there's
this unrolling generative model that's
getting light touches from the sensory
information getting fine-tuned that's
the sort of like inside out view of
experience as opposed to a sensory
processing I mean sensory processing
even as a as a framework makes it sound
like the information is out there and
we're going to like process the wheat
separate the wheat from the chaff and
then we're going to end up with like
just the real you know we're going to
have the pixels on the camera and then
we're going to process the pixels and
figure out whether it's a cat or a dog
or um even further like we're going to
process the pixels and then we're going
to figure out what to do um as opposed
to we're going to have this unfolding
model about how things are and their
likelihoods and and what to do and then
we're going to get get just light
touches from sensory data and um I guess
the trip is that
um if we believe that sensory processing
is outside in the world will confirm our
beliefs I think there's a few truth
drops just in the visual experience that
help us understand the Inside Out
perception so the first is the blind
spot which we don't attend to it's
filled in perfectly even though there's
a large um patch on the retina that
doesn't get that much visual input
second one is that in the periphery
there are uh fewer um there's lower
resolution vision and there's no color
vision however in healthy Vision we have
color and equal resolution and there's
experiments that show like actually well
it is lower resolution in the periphery
but it's not attended to as such and
then we just look over and then the
third aspect is the Cade so multiple
times per second our eyes are
moving and with active inference we can
understand okay it's like we're when the
Gaze is fixed our Precision is high and
we're getting we're paying more
attention to visual input and then right
before we're ready to execute a cade of
course this is subconscious Precision is
alleviated the eye moves and then it's
like the the foot goes back on the gaps
so the fact that the blind spot the
periphery and the
secades are not attended to
is is very um
tangible that just our visual
experience is what we generate it to
be with of course information coming
from what's
external but it's not being processed
merely from what's
external okay so let let's go to s's
question
here um how are action and perception
similar different or
related what's anything that that anyone
wants to add on this or there's a few
pieces to bring
in the part about the planning
um you know is that in between or is
that part of
action got great
question well
so um uh Kristoff brought up the Hubble
and whizzle experiments with the cat
retina and the selectivities
um in different brain regions and that
actually connects to one of the most
cited uh Neuroscience papers certainly
within the ACT INF space which is r and
Ballard
99 which provided some of the early
strong evidence for predictive coding
and so like well so in that retina
experiment they had classical patterns
like classical cell types oh this one
responds to vertical lines this one
responds to diagonal lines this one's
horizontal or so on however there were
these receptive
Fields like patterns of activation of
visual neurons that were extra classical
like they were not accounted for within
a classical receptive field model and
this
paper with empirical evidence and and
mathematical
modeling established that predictive
coding which is to say like expectations
about visual input were able to account
for some of these extra classical
phenomena
um
Andrew oh yeah I just wanted to say just
very generally on the the action
perception relationship um active
inference seems to take the stance that
like we are actively inferring
information around us and so rather than
being like passive observers who are
just sitting there we we engage in
actions in order to um kind of impact
our perception such as like you pick
something up and look at it like you can
look at it from different angles all of
those are like actions that you're
taking um that's that's my general sense
of the relationship between the two as
opposed to some classical view that
we're just you know sitting there we're
taking in whatever the supposed reality
is around us we're not actually doing
anything we're just observers um that's
it I don't know if that tracks yeah
thank you um Jesse then
Manuel yeah I think I mean isn't the the
two options either you change your mind
or you change the world to minimize the
free energy
so um that's kind of how I see it
anything that you do that act that
changes the World materially falls in
the category of action
where um changing your mind is
perception I guess what I'm struggling
with is that your mind is in the world
right so you say you change your mind
but that's the same thing as changing
the world like I'm still struggling with
the the difference because changing your
mind it's just okay even even if we
reduce it to it's changing firing rates
it's changing patterns in in neurons
it's not some esoteric mind concept it's
still something physical we're changing
there's a action there to change the the
synchrony between different brain
regions or whatever it is that causes
that sort of perceptual switch but it's
not like an esoteric concept it's a it's
still something physical that's changing
is what I'm struggling with and but I I
completely get what you're saying like I
do agree with that but then when you the
smaller and smaller you get it's like
what is changing your mind it's just a
changing weights between neurons it's
changing synchrony it's changing
something physical unless unless you
know maybe this will be the answer and
we'll find something metaphysical
finally in the in the brain
somehow awesome menw well and
then yeah just to give my two sents on
this point I think is really interesting
what s is saying but you know in the
formalism uh where the free energy
principle comes from my understanding is
you know you have to define a a
dynamical system which has many
variables and for this thing to apply
there has to be a concept of a mark of
blanket which will come later in the
book but it's like you have a separation
of variables that do not have direct
contact with other variables within the
system only through through this this
layer of
interaction and perception and action
are different there in the
directionality of the influences so
perception only influences the internal
state of the subsystem you care about uh
but doesn't do the opposite and or or
the sorry the the internal system
doesn't influence the perception States
and the opposite with action and when
you say yeah like the brain also is
taking an action in in a physical world
and that's true you know Freestone seems
to mention pretty often how these Mark
of blankets I think of them as you know
the mataska the Russian doll many layers
of these uh Mark of blankets on top of
each other so a cell it's doing its own
uh active inference but it's so it's had
its own Mark of blanket maybe defined by
its own cellular membrane and whatnot
but it's part of a circuit and that
circuit is also has now a more
functional Mark of blanket and it and
and they take uh take actions towards
other systems and and and you know many
many scales of this kind of thing but
the I think the more precise difference
is this of of what variables are
changing in your system versus what
variables you change of what is not the
system all defined by what the mark of
blanket is always in the in the sense
that there has to be something that is
that you care about and some and the
rest that you don't care about directly
yes very interesting and important point
which is a a simple or narrow technical
difference between action and perception
is for a given system of interest that
we're just going to focus on the inbound
dependencies are perceptual the outbound
dependencies are action and then with a
different
blanket or a different system of
Interest a given causal influence might
be under understood as well you know it
was an action for this for the speaker
but then it was a perception for The
Listener so then by taking uh uh by by
swapping a
perspective um we might give a different
AC INF onology tag to the same causal
Edge on a base
graph um raw and then
Andrew yeah I was thinking a bit about
this uh after I got to figure 2.2 in the
textbook um because they're the figures
they're
illustrating this
um uh this interface or this this
influence that uh an agent has uh on the
World
to uh generate some kind of uh
observations why here and
in my mind the difference between
perception is in action
is at least based on the formalism that
we're given here is in the access that
we have to the hidden States so out in
the world there's there's some some
process some generative process as they
refer to it and and there's no way to
observe though that uh the hidden states
of that gener generative process and the
hidden states are are the causes of
whatever uh observations you have so for
example if you see an apple there's
something out there in the world that is
generating Apple like observations on
your retina and then uh inside of your
mind you have some also you have a
generative model of what that uh process
is in out in the world but you actually
have some um maybe some influence some
more direct influence over that uh over
the configuration of the generative
model and uh so even if you you take
some actions internally to update that
model it's uh it's different than than
like uh some proxy action that you take
to change your observations out in the
world um that's as far as the
distinction has have been clear enough
to me but I think this idea of a mark
off blanket which will probably Explore
More
um on in the high road to active
inference uh I think that's also a deep
an important idea
for establishing what it means to be uh
a system what it means to be a thing
that that is separate in some uh
significant way in some statistical
way perhaps from from the external
world thank you great Point even if we
chose to take a kind of active modeling
approach to internal action like through
attention or whether even conceptualized
of learning as action like just the
actual parameter updating of learning
not just like moving around in the world
only through the agent's boundary would
the object be intervened upon in the
world it'd be like you know if people
are watching a movie and they're they
might be doing intentional modulation or
something they're not intervening with
what's on the movie
screen versus an outgoing dependency
which is to say real over to
action then um does modify how hidden
States changed their
time
Andrew sorry um yeah know I think
everyone just before me largely Su up
what I wanted to say I guess I'll just
add um another way I kind of think about
it um is like the inclusion of the the
idea of preferences and the generative
model carries preferences um and in
differentiating the um the system of
Interest like the model versus the
process whose true States we don't have
direct access to and so on um like you
know for me a human is a generative
model like I have references or
homeostatic set points or however you
want to view those so I want to keep my
Hunger low I would like to get some good
sleep I would like to have a well
regulated body temperature and um while
I would say yes my body my mind and so
on are in fact part and parcel with the
world I'm in the world I don't think
that the world around me has the same
preferences I do I don't think it's
attempting to uh regulate my body and uh
maintain my home ostatic set points I
have to engage in in action as well as
like attempting to get rather tractable
accurate perceptions of the World Around
Me In order to act and and uh realize my
preferences that are you know all of
these
homeostatic um set points um active
inference seems to paint the process
around the model potentially is just
like an entropic dissipative set of
forces that the agent is trying to act
against um in some ways and that's not
necessarily a big antagonistic picture
between us and the world around us but
in some ways yeah we do have to kind of
um fight for our lives something like
that
so yeah great
points um you
could specify a generative model where
the environment was just at the exact
temperature that the agent
preferred or you could have one where
the environment had some regions that
were the preferred temperature and some
that weren't and then that would lead to
the question of well then how would the
agent select where to move and that
would take us literally exactly to
expected free energy where pragmatic
value
would um upweight or
upregulate policy selection that led to
observations aligning with
preferences but again to to this top
question
um AC action and perception certainly
work
together that is a kind of way
preactive Insight that that there's this
um inextricable relationship between
perception and action like the
um uh even the opening quote of the
chapter by William James is connecting
thinking and and doing
[Music]
um however they're
not the
same we've talked about how for a given
system of Interest their directions are
different across a
blanket um
they're they're also modeled as
different in the generative model that
we specify like this is looking to
figure
4.3 but
perception is going to be
loaded in between observations and
hidden States so perception is going to
be just from a from what variables you
you actually use it's it's mediating the
relationship between observations and
unobserved latent causes like here's the
thermometer reading and then here's the
estimate of what temperature it is in
the room that's where perception is
whereas action is seen as intervening in
how hidden States change through time
you're not reaching in and changing how
the thermometer reading is related to
temperature in the abstract you're
actually doing something that modifies
how temperature in the world changes
through time and then the thermometer
readings might be different later so it
it action and perception are coming in
differently to how we specify the
generative
model uh Susan or or anyone
else yeah so here's how I'm kind of
interpreting the the planning um and
this kind of brings in you the ch
changing your world changing your mind
versus changing your world um so
changing the world if I'm if if I'm
trying to change my world then I'm
acting on the environment and if I if it
you know if there's um um and bringing
in the expected ambiguity and risk
that's what's
emerging and if you know if I'm not able
to reach the expectations of what's
changing in the world then that's going
to bring me back back to changing my
mind so that planning is you know is um
is the the inferences that I have about
what my power in the world is and I
think that you to for me that's kind of
where I bring in the affordances because
you the what you talked about Andrew was
was I interpreted that as you someone
feels
entitled um that the world's going to
provide them and then they act out in
the world world as if they're entitled
they may well you know either have to
change their mind or they're going to
get reinforcement that they are
entitled is that is that
cohere yeah like if there's a door and
one expects to be on the other side of
the door then it's like you try to open
the door okay if it opens then you
change the world and then you proceed on
and as you described like then that was
like confirmed or reinforced whereas if
it doesn't open I mean what I got to get
back changing my mind yeah you could
keep on trying but at some point if it's
not
openable there's going to have to be a
belief update that that in that moment
at the very
least that door can't be open otherwise
it's going to be just you know you're
gonna um not drink any water and you're
going to die trying to open that door
it's like there has to be a stopping
point um and and that brings in the
expected ambiguity plus
risk yes let's definitely this yes we'll
look at 2.5 2.6 and see what um where
these come in um
Andrew hi uh multitasking again um just
a quick
question this act action perception
conversation reminded me I have some
questions about attention and intention
do are those Concepts kind of covered or
addressed anywhere in active inference
or this
textbook attention absolutely in its
more uh technical parametric meaning of
attention as precision as well as in its
kind of broader
psychological uh meaning
intention probably more of a nebulous
concept so not to say that you couldn't
um
assign preferences to be intentions for
example the belief desire intention
model that's explored in live stream 46
by Ryan Smith at all where they
associate preferences just
straightforwardly um W with they talk
about the generative model in terms of
the belief desire intention folk
psychology model but in this textbook
it's um going to certainly talk about
attention and that's a major
topic cool yeah I was just noticing the
other day how um with your perceptions
there's certain modalities like your
sense Your Skin Sense and your body
sense that can be masked um in terms of
perception in a way that like noise
cannot from your conscious experience
and I thought that might say something
interesting about the active inference
model or the the structure in our
brains
yes cool yeah that this is uh
6.2 here's like different kinds of
observations so Sensor Fusion setting
and then
attention is it allocated across sensory
modalities or how is it or where is it
distributed
across um or within sensory
modalities how are those attentions
to
observations related to like Bel
unexperienced beliefs about the
world like you're not actually directly
experiencing whether there's a jumping
frog but you may experience interception
auditory visual
um
Jesse could you look at to Andrew's
question could you look at policy as
intention more or less because you know
it's projecting a series of actions that
you aren't you know that you'd like to
uh have happen but I was thinking that
exact same
thing so there's a quote on um page 38 I
believe
um where they're
discussing beliefs over
policies as intention and this is
related to the
expected uh free
energy
um
formalism and yeah I think this is an
interesting quote to discuss if people
have any thoughts about
it nice great reference
there
I don't know if this is two two general
the statements
but it it to to go from something that
is uh Technical and within the ACT INF
onology and then kind of like zoom out
or adapt it to a more nebulous
setting that's that's on you like if you
choose to take that interpretation of a
given aspect of active inference in a
setting
then it'll it'll be valid in the ways
that it's valid for that setting and it
won't be the whole story in the ways
that it's not the whole story for that
setting however that kind of a
question is difficult to answer in the
abstract because when we're talking
about policy selection we're talking
about metronomes and particles of dust
and computers and groups of people so so
then if but so if someone's thinking
well intention I'm meaning like what I
experience when I want to do something
then you're already in the case of a
given system of interest at which point
it's no longer like a general question
about the ACT INF onology it's more
about how you're adapting a term or an
equation or something to a given
setting at which point it'll be useful
how it's
useful and it'll be not the whole story
in the ways that it isn't um Andrew
sorry I never um unraised my hand but I
I do actually have a comment on that um
related to policy one thing I maybe this
is discussed in later uh chapters but
policy generation it seems like at least
in these early equations there
there a set of policies is in inferred
but I don't see how policies are
generated is is that discussed or
implied
somewhere yeah good question it connects
to the where is planning so
[Music]
um
policies just as a first pass answer
policies are the affordances that are
available multiplied by how many uh
to to the exponent of how many time
steps the planning Horizon is so if
their affordances are up down left right
there four
affordances over one time step there's
four policies that can be selected up
down left right so for a Time Horizon of
one affordances and policies are
identical for a Time Horizon of two
you'd have 16 policies of length to up
up up down up right up left
Etc um so in this setting policies are
just
affordances over a horizon so then how
do I'm not I'm not sure that really
answers it unless affordances are
generated because it just moves the
question absolutely so how are
affordances learned or how are they
provided so like in the teamas or
something like that it's like how does
the rat know that it can move up down
left right so first we're dealing with
maps not territories so just specifying
a given Vector of affordances doesn't
mean that the rat knows that it can do
those affordances or has any kind of
like awareness uh about them it's just
us describing what we've seen the system
do so we're when we're talking about the
afford the policy prior or or the Habit
Vector the prior
on um
affordances those are something that the
modeler infers not necessarily the
system of Interest
itself however it still is the question
of Interest well how are those
affordances known and H what happens
when it it up down left right and then
all of a sudden up down left right and
raise up you
know an arm or something like that like
how do new affordances come into
play
we can express the question in the ACT
infology
but write it out for a given system of
interest and then I think you'll be well
closer to the
answer but certainly you can develop
nested models where like there's a um a
a a context shift that leads to a
different set of
affordances but but that's a that's um a
good
question let's look at 2.5 and 2.6 and
just look at their
partitionings
okay so here's
2. five and they write that variational
free energy so variational it just means
we're using variational methods so we're
doing approximate basian computation not
exact Baye but approximate Baye using
variational
methods it may seem an abstract concept
but its nature and role it plays in
active becomes apparent when decomposed
into quantities that are more intuitive
and familiar in cognitive
science so
these
three
lines are different
decompositions of variational free
energy so they differently partition the
kind of
same
piie in a few
ways the
top line is more of a statistical
physics
decomposition that is most like for
example Gibbs free energy for those with
a chemistry background
whereas the second and third
line have more to do with Statistics and
model fitting and in both cases I mean
ultimately in all cases since they're
describing the exact same quantity but
especially um in this pure statistical
second and third
decompositions it highlights that we're
fitting data but also not one to overfit
data and the family of distributions
that are being utilized are whatever are
used for Q Q is the distribution that we
control from the family that we selected
so if we say we're going to do
variational inference on temperature in
this room and we're going to use a
gaussian distribution so like a a a bell
curve
distribution that doesn't mean that the
temperature in the
room is act
changing according to a bell curve or
that the thermometer is giving us
readings according to that Gan
distribution maybe it has like a long
tail or maybe it has some other
distribution but it means that we are
going to have our hands on the knobs of
Q and get to the best fitting which is
to say anything wider would be underfit
anything tighter would be
overfit those are the knobs that we can
control it might be grossly inadequate
but there is a way to fit the best
possible
Q to a given Y data and the way to fit
the best Q to a
y is with reducing the K Divergence
shown here and that is variational free
energy
minimization if you can reduce that K
Divergence between the variational free
energy and
surprise to zero then variational
inference is identical to exact basian
inference because minimizing surprise is
kind of like the actual Target here if
you minimize surprise you've maximized
model evidence you know you're getting
new thermometer readings coming in if
you were minimally surprised by those
readings you would have the highest
model evidence you would have the best
belief
so instead of trying to maximize model
evidence directly with like a hill
climbing approach statistical physics
kind of inverts that problem and says
well let's think about going downhill
with a gradient
descent and here is our way to like have
a tractable
incrementally improvable
approach that we know is going to be
moving in the right direction to
surprise minimization with variational
free energy minimization which is highly
optimizable again doesn't mean that it's
going to get exactly here doesn't even
mean it'll get
close but you will be able to take
incremental improving moves which is
kind of shown
here so that's the real
time beliefs the approximate posterior q
and the incoming data y That's the
variational free energy and again the
first decomposition is more like
statistical physics free energies and
the second and third decompositions are
more like
statistics this doesn't have anything to
do with the future this is just like a
real time
unfolding then we get into expected free
energy so expected free energy extends
active inference to include a
prospective form of cognition which is
planning so now um rather than just the
kind of ball rolling down the hill okay
sometimes it jumps left sometimes it
jumps right but each time its movement
is basically um dictated or constrained
by its local surroundings so we could
talk about that ball having policy
decisions or taking actions in some sort
of um
very like real- time unfolding way but
we might not need to appeal to planning
however we may be interested in
cognitive models that have an explicit
planning component like deliberation or
consideration of multiple
decisions again this isn't to say that
that system does planning just that
we're going to make a cognitive model
that includes the planning
component um key notation is when
there's a Tilda little curve curvy line
over a variable that is being used to
refer to like a Ser a whole time series
of that variable over a given time
Horizon
so now we move from F of Q and Y
variational free energy to G of Pi so
it's different in a bunch of different
ways expected free energy looking to the
future with these series of expected
hidden States and observations that of
course have not happened yet whereas
variational free energy was dealing with
the actual data
why we also noticed that expected free
energy
is taking in as an
argument policy
priors not taking in beliefs and data
directly but rather even though we see
the Q and the Y but what G is doing most
proximately is taking in the prior on
policy so this is like a vector of all
the possible
policies again if it was only one time
step that's the same as the affordances
if it was two time steps it would be
like affordances squared taking in the
prior Distribution on those policies and
then sharpening or reweighting them
according to
this so let's think about that up down
left right two time step settings so 16
policies so if we had no a priori habit
of any of those they would all be like
116th
and that Vector would look like 16 tall
and each value would be
116th or if we always did policy one and
two and then we very rarely did the
other ones it would be like 0.5 point5
and all zeros or you might put that in a
computer as like
04949 and then very small values for
things that are rarely
done G takes in that policy prior and it
updates it
according to this
calculation and so for people who want
to look at the code that's very helpful
to see where exactly this comes into
play takes in that vector and then it
sharpens or updates
it to give more weight make the policy
posterior bigger
where where the policy contributes
Information Gain or price Matic value
pragmatic value Rewards or updates or
increases the waiting on policies that
bring expected future observations into
alignment with
preferences that is the definition of
pragmatic
value the definition of Information Gain
or epistemic value is about the
difference that you're expected
to um get
depending on the observations that you
expect to
see so it's definitely a
lot however that is what this
top and most common decomposition of
expected free energy
does and then as Susan brought up
another decomposition of
G is rather than thinking about what G
does as upweighting based upon epistemic
impra Matic value you could think about
G as changing the The Waiting of
policies based upon their expected
ambiguities and
risk um David and then
Andrew hi I guess a
major a major obstacle for me to
understand all of this is literally the
mathematic construction of this sentence
so like I I for example here I just
don't know where the what the ti means
in X and Y or what where the C comes
from just ask me because I don't know if
somebody has this sense of
discomfort not being able to decode what
what's this trying to tell me and I
don't know if somebody have some good
resource on how to really understand
this this
construction yeah thanks for asking
totally agreed
um hopefully you're in a good resource
now and thank you again for
asking depending on someone's
familiarity with math or computer
science and programming there's
definitely a lot of approaches but the
big approach is many coats of paint like
coar grain it just say Okay 2.6 is
expected fore energy and you can go down
fractal rabbit holes for the rest of
your life or at some point you can just
say Okay expected for fre energy is
about updating beliefs about action
another really helpful resource that
again I incourage people to contribute
to is the natural language descriptions
of the
questions it's a lot easier to
read there's still a lot of terms in
here but the blue terms are ones where
we have Mouse over
definitions um and then also maybe
someone's interested in playing around
more with the
AI explanations that we used these may
be helpful um
certainly on your own notebook or
however like the
notation uh and understanding like you
know Q approximate posterior x hidden
States Through Time y observations
Through Time Pi policy it is like
learning a vocabulary or a symbol
matching exercise um and math is a
language and acin is a dialect so it
just is a lot of
exposure
and hearing about it Kristoff they pull
the equation out of the
Hat yeah in in in some ways yes also the
textbook is
uh is distilling and summarizing across
research and there are more lengthy
derivations
elsewhere the the math learning group
again to the extent that people want to
to do these
activities um there's always been like a
more fundamentals of math learning group
side like just like what does it mean
when we have two matrices and then we
just like put them next to each other
like what what does that mean to
multiply them and then also some people
like Jonathan and Ali and others have
worked on the derivations of the
equations and sanj N josi's textbook and
other resources help so it's just like
but being in the game is the key
enabling step um
Andrew yeah um actually kind of related
to this uh just one toide for some of
the Greek characters as soon as I start
like memorizing what the pronunciation
of the characters are you find that
there is a mapping between like me and
mind there's some alliteration going on
um so that might be a little pneumonic
to help um the other thing is I was
wondering with the assignment of like um
epistemic value to part of these
equations is that a generally agreed
upon format Within in the sort of
scientific body or was that sort of
arbitrarily mapped by the researchers um
putting these equations
together so so like those statistical
yeah um beian sort of uh equations is
that like agreed upon as um denoting
that qualitative uh term
in the case of variational free energy
yes I'd say it's absolutely non-c
contentious variational basian methods
or energy based methods with these
decompositions have been in play for
decades expected free energy extends
vfe
into the discussion of observations that
have not happened
yet also these are non-c contentious
decompositions I believe I don't know I
don't have any survey data on on who
knows or believes what but but I don't
think that these are
contentious about the latch there is a
column
here um if you want the raw
latch that is a a good
technique you can paste this into yeah
gp4 can use images as
input um this is why the stigar G is so
important the notes that people write in
the questions like the more that people
add the more material there are for
human and non-human
Learners um and we make do and we stay
in the game with what we have like three
or six months ago when we were
converting the m to latch this was the
best that we could
do and it works really well with Cod AI
Cod AI does not have the image
recognition yet but if slash when they
do we'll be able to add
another column and just say Okay given
what's in the
figure dot dot dot dot
dot so yeah lot of different interesting
emerging ways
to work with the
material cool so that is
um chapter
two on the low
road for the next two
weeks we'll head into chapter 3 on the h
so thank you everyone see you next
time thank you thank you bye thank you
this is great